Hi everyone.
For those who don’t know me yet,
I’m Kristine Dennis,
a scientist who has
spent my career
working in public health
and nutrition research.
At NutritionFacts, I serve as
Senior Research Scientist
and, alongside Dr. Greger,
research and write
new video scripts.
For these next couple of videos,
I got to take a deep dive into the
research on raising plant-based kids.
As a parent of a plant-
based kid myself
and a nutrition research nerd,
this was both fun and fascinating.
I’m going to cover everything
that goes into raising kids
on well-planned
plant-based diets,
including what does
‘well-planned’ actually mean,
some potential benefits of eating
plant-based during pregnancy,
and a few special nutrients everyone
should be paying attention to
— regardless of diet.
"Preventing Gestational Diabetes
During Pregnancy with Diet"
Over the past two decades,
scientific and
professional nutrition,
and pediatric associations,
have issued official statements
and published position papers
about adopting vegan diets
during crucial life stages,
including pregnancy
and lactation,
infancy, and childhood.
While some of these associations
firmly agree
a well-designed vegan diet
can be healthy and support
normal growth and development,
others are more reserved,
and some caution against
vegan diets for children.
Those that are supportive
include the American
Dietetic Association,
which has held this position
for more than 25 years,
as well as
professional associations
in Australia, Canada,
Portugal, Italy,
the UK, Finland,
Germany, and Norway,
and Europe more broadly.
More reserved opinions
also came out of the UK
and Europe, including Spain,
and downright
dismissive positions
have come out of Slovenia,
Germany, Italy,
France, and Belgium.
What does the evidence say
about vegan diets in children?
Part of the challenge
starts at the very beginning,
with the exclusion
of pregnant people
from clinical trials in general.
With such compelling needs,
why are pregnant women
largely excluded
from clinical research?
Often due to ethical concerns,
dominated by fears
of fetal harm.
Even non-pregnant women
of reproductive age
often have to commit
to contraception
during the research period,
and those who become pregnant
must leave the study
with their data excluded.
That all adds up to a lack
of clinical trial data
on pregnant women.
Paradoxically,
these precautionary measures
may not have made pregnant moms
or their babies safer
because of the resulting
lack of evidence.
Some of the commentary
around vegan diets for children
includes this same concern
about the lack of data.
One researcher stated,
"In children we do not
have many good quality studies,
and the studies we do have come
mostly from vegetarian children,
and they are of
very varying quality."
But researchers are
attempting to fill this void,
starting with,
"To vegan or not to vegan
when pregnant, lactating,
or feeding young children."
The oldest
and largest association
of nutritional professionals
in the world,
the Academy
of Nutrition and Dietetics
considers a completely
plant-based diet
to be suitable during pregnancy,
lactation, infancy,
and childhood,
provided it is well-planned.
What exactly
does well-planned mean?
First of all, a diet
rich in a wide variety
of plant foods;
grains, legumes
(such as beans, lentils,
split peas, and chickpeas),
fruits and veggies,
nuts and seeds,
herbs and spices.
We want to limit vegetable fats
so they don't displace
more nutrient-dense foods,
and if you do use them,
choosing them carefully,
for example, avoiding
trans fats and tropical oils.
Also taking a DHA supplement,
consuming enough calcium,
and ensuring
sufficient vitamin D.
And most importantly,
not forgetting
about vitamin B12,
as Dr. Greger
has covered extensively
because it is so important
to ensure a regular
and reliable source
of vitamin B12.
Balanced plant-based diets
mean eating a wide
variety of plant foods
in order to sufficiently
meet energy requirements,
and paying attention
to some nutrients
that may be critical,
iodine included.
It's one nutrient that
should also be supplemented
during pregnancy
and breastfeeding.
What are the impacts
on the mother's health
of following a vegetarian diet
during pregnancy?
Gestational diabetes
affects around 14 percent
of pregnancies globally,
and even more
in some regions of the world.
It's also at the center
of the vicious cycle
of diabetes begetting diabetes.
Linked not only
to adverse pregnancy
and birth outcomes,
but greater long-term risk
of cardiometabolic disorders
for both moms and babies.
Research suggests
beneficial impacts
of plant-based diets
on blood sugar control.
What effect might that have
on risk of gestational diabetes?
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
on plant-based
dietary patterns
and gestational diabetes risk
found that those who ate
closer to a healthy,
plant-based diet
had a significantly lower risk
of developing
gestational diabetes.
Evidence from the
Harvard Nurses' Health Study II
suggests these benefits extend
to hypertensive disorders,
like preeclampsia,
with a 20 percent lower risk
among those eating
the most plant-based diets.
And this lower risk
could benefit moms' health
for years to come,
as hypertensive disorders
during pregnancy
are associated with
increased risk of stroke
later in life.
Note that Dr. Greger
previously covered
other pregnancy
outcomes, as well.
Once the baby arrives,
what do we know about
plant-based diets
and feeding babies
and young children?
I'll cover that next.